Guide to the Jacquard Weaving Treatises
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Jacquard weaving treatises
1771-1947
1855-1947
GEN MSS 1092
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.29
(19 boxes)
Manuscript treatises and notes on weaving with Jacquard looms, containing instructions, illustrations of looms, cloth swatches, thread samples, and punch card patterns. Eighteen treatises in French were created by students for coursework at the École de tissage de Lyon, France, 1855-1947, some including printed descriptions of Jacquard and Verdol looms, technical drawings of looms, other printed material relating to weaving in Lyon, and diagrams of punch cards. Notes in German, 1829-1832, are bound with a printed copy of Kirschbaum, Johann Michael, Neues Bild- und Musterbuch zur Beförderung der edlen Leinen- und Bildweberkunst: in 178 Mustern auf 74 Kupfertafeln (Heilbronn und Rothenburg ob der Tauber, in der Eckebrechtischen Buchhandlung, 1771). A manuscript treatise in German, 1894-1895, is accompanied by manuscript notes; two printed articles about the Sächsische Webstuhlfabrik in Chemnitz, Germany, and Louis Ferdinand Schönherr, with technical drawings of looms, undated; two blueprint technical drawings of looms, undated; and a watercolor drawing of "Howard & Bullough's Sizing Machine," undated.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from William Reese Co. on the Adrian Van Sinderen, '10 Fund, 2007 and 2012.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Jacquard Loom
The Jacquard loom, invented by Joseph-Marie Jacquard in 1804, used a system of punch cards to weave patterned cloth. The Jacquard loom was employed by the textile industry worldwide during the 19th-20th centuries, and its system of punch cards influenced development of punch card technology for computers.
Scope and Contents
Manuscript treatises and notes on weaving with Jacquard looms, containing instructions, illustrations of looms, cloth swatches, thread samples, and punch card patterns. Eighteen treatises in French were created by students for coursework at the École de tissage de Lyon, France, 1855-1947, some including printed descriptions of Jacquard and Verdol looms, technical drawings of looms, other printed material relating to weaving in Lyon, and diagrams of punch cards. Notes in German, 1829-1832, are bound with a printed copy of Kirschbaum, Johann Michael, Neues Bild- und Musterbuch zur Beförderung der edlen Leinen- und Bildweberkunst: in 178 Mustern auf 74 Kupfertafeln (Heilbronn und Rothenburg ob der Tauber, in der Eckebrechtischen Buchhandlung, 1771). A manuscript treatise in German, 1894-1895, is accompanied by manuscript notes; two printed articles about the Sächsische Webstuhlfabrik in Chemnitz, Germany, and Louis Ferdinand Schönherr, with technical drawings of looms, undated; two blueprint technical drawings of looms, undated; and a watercolor drawing of "Howard & Bullough's Sizing Machine," undated.
Arrangement
Arranged chronologically.
Information technology -- France; Information technology -- Germany; Jacquard weaving -- France; Jacquard weaving -- France -- Lyon; Jacquard weaving -- Germany -- Chemnitz; Punched card systems -- Weaving; Textile industry -- France -- Lyon; Textile industry -- Germany -- Chemnitz; Weaving -- France -- Study and teaching; Weaving -- Germany -- Study and teaching; Swatches -- France -- 19th century; Swatches -- France -- 20th Century; Swatches -- Germany -- 19th century; Technical drawings -- France -- 19th century; Technical drawings -- France -- 20th Century; Technical drawings -- Germany -- 19th century; Jacquard, Joseph-Marie, 1752-1834; Kirschbaum, Johann Michael, 1725-1782; Schönherr, Louis Ferdinand, 1817-1911; École de tissage de Lyon; Howard & Bullough; Sächsische Webstuhlfabrik
- Bübmann, Wilhelm Friedrich. Notes and printed material, in German, 1771-1832 and undated (Box 15)
  Scope and Contents
  Includes manuscript punch card patterns, 1828-1832 and undated, on printed grids (Nuremberg: in der Johann Andreae Endterischen Handlung, undated).
  On cover: "Kunst ... für Johann Georg Bübmann. Webermeister ...."
  Bound with: Kirschbaum, Johann Michael. Neues Bild- und Musterbuch zur Beförderung der edlen Leinen- und Bildweberkunst: in 178 Mustern auf 74 Kupfertafeln (Heilbronn und Rothenburg ob der Tauber, in der Eckebrechtischen Buchhandlung, 1771)
- Laurent, Jules. "Cahier de théorie appartenant à Jules Laurent: commencé le mardi, 9 janvier, 1855" (Box 1)
- Laurent, Jules. "Cahier de théorie appartenant à Jules Laurent: commencé le mardi, 9 janvier, 1855." Punch card patterns and cloth swatches formerly laid in, undated (Box 14, Folder 1)
- Toscanelli, A., fils. "Théorie. 1", circa 1860s (Box 2)
  Affixed to inside front cover: autograph letter, signed, from Toscanelli, Lyon, to "Monsieur," 186[?] December 10
- Unidentified. Untitled treatise on Jacquard weaving, in French, circa 1870 (Box 3)
- Anselme, E. "Cours de theorie pour le tissage professe par P. Audibert, fait par E. Anselme", 1872 (Box 16)
  Includes watercolor drawings of looms and a photograph of punch cards.
- Unidentified. Untitled treatise on Jacquard weaving, in German, 1894 November 4-1895 April 27 (Box 14, Folder 2)
- Unidentified. Untitled treatise on Jacquard weaving, in German. Notes, printed articles, and drawings formerly laid in, undated (Box 14, Folder 3)
  Includes: manuscript notes; printed articles about the Sächsische Webstuhlfabrik, in Chemnitz, Germany, and Louis Ferdinand Schönherr, with technical drawings of looms, undated; blueprint technical drawings of looms, undated; and a watercolor drawing of "Howard & Bullough's Sizing Machine," undated.
- Lelouvetel, Paul. "Cours basse-lisse", 1896 January 14-1897 February 1 (Box 4)
- Veyle, René de. "Cours de théorie", circa 1900 (Box 5)
- Unidentified. "Premiers principes de la fabrication des tissus", circa 1900 (Box 6)
- Unidentified. "Théorie de tissage", circa 1900 (Box 7)
- Unidentified. "Cour de tissage. 1re année", [1906] (Box 17)
- Unidentified. "Cour de tissage. 2me année", [1907] (Box 18)
  Tipped in: printed descriptions of Jacquard and Verdol looms, and diagrams of punch cards
- Unidentified. "Cour de tissage. 2me année." Punch card, notes, drawings, and printed material formerly laid in, 1928-1929, undated (Box 14, Folder 7)
  Includes: punch card; manuscript notes; printed technical drawings of looms; other printed material relating to weaving and Lyon, some with, with fabric samples.
- Unidentified. "Cour de tissage. 2me année." Printed material formerly laid in, undated (Box 19 (Oversize))
- Unidentified. Cour de tissage. 1re année. "Cour de tissage. II année," notebook, formerly laid in, 1907 October 15 (Box 14, Folder 6)
- Chauvin, F. "École municipale de tissage de la ville de Lyon, année 1909-1910. Cours de tissage" (Box 8)
- Caton, C. "Cours de tissage", circa 1910 (Box 9)
- Unidentified. Untitled treatise on Jacquard weaving, in French, circa 1910 (Box 10)
  Tipped in: printed descriptions of Jacquard and Verdol looms, technical drawings of looms, and diagrams of punch cards
- Loir, J. B. "Théorie de tissage des étoffes de soie: unis: premiére année", 1923-1924 (Box 11)
- Loir, J. B. "Théorie de tissage des etoffes de soie: façonnès: deuxième année", 1924-1925 (Box 12)
- Guerrier, J, diplômé de L'École de tassage. "E. M. T.: année 1925-1926: professeur F. Guiberd" (Box 13)
- Marthoud, A. "Cours de creation de tissus", circa 1940 (Box 14, Folder 4)
- Tallon, Jacques, 1ère E. S. T. "École de tissage - Lyon: Théorie du tissage", 1946-1947 (Box 14, Folder 5)